Guide to the Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn records ARC.131
Brooklyn Historical Society
Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn records
1834 - 1998
Center for Brooklyn History
Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn
Brookwood Child Care
Collins, Janna
ARC.131
7 Linear Feet in four manuscript boxes, two book boxes, two oversize boxes, and three flat file folders.
The Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn records, dated 1834 to 1998, contains the annual reports, photographs, and register of the Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn, later named Brookwood Child Care.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan.
Series 4 is closed for research. See the Conditions Governing Access note at that level for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accession 2005.012 is the gift of Janna Collins, 2005. Manuals from 1902-1924 were transferred to the Long Island Historical Society in 1927 by Carrie Adams, Secretary to the Board of Managers at the Orphan Asylum. The immediate source of acquistion for the other accessions is unknown.
Arrangement
The records are organized in five series:
Series 1: Annual reports and manuals, 1834-1998
Series 2: Promotional materials, circa 1910-1986
Series 3: Citations and proclamations, 1983-1990
Series 4: Register and certificates of indenture, 1855-1974
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1900-circa 1990
Historical note
The Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn was founded in 1833 by a group of wealthy Brooklynites in response to an 1832 cholera epidemic, which left many children as orphans. The Orphan Asylum Society cared for children who were destitute or orphaned, offering shelter, food, and schooling. Throughout the 19th century, the society housed children until adulthood, or arranged indentures to families outside of Brooklyn.
The asylum moved several times due to overpopulation. Its original location was at the Jackson Mansion on Willow Street and Love Lane in Brooklyn Heights. In 1869, the Society bought 47 lots at the intersection of Atlantic and Kingston Avenues and moved into the new building in 1872. The organization moved out to Brookwood Hall in East Islip, NY in 1942. In 1952, a new branch of the society named Brookwood Child Care opened on Adelphi Street in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn, offering adoptions, foster care, and social services to families in Brooklyn and other boroughs. Brookwood Child Care sold Brookwood Hall in 1965, leaving only their Brookwood Child Care offices on Adelphi Street. The society continued operation under the Brookwood name until its dissolution in 2006.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragility of the volumes, bound Manuals should only be used when the needed year is not represented among the unbound Manuals.
Scope and Contents
The Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn records, dated 1834 to 1998, contains the annual reports and register of the Orphan Asylum Society related to its locations in Brooklyn and Brookwood Hall in East Islip, NY. The bulk of the collection is annual reports, by-laws, and regulations, which provide financial data, advisory board member names, and personnel information. While lists of contributors and society members are provided in annual reports, names of children in the society's care are not provided.
The Orphan Asylum and Brookwood Hall Register, dated 1907 to 1974, lists orphan names, dates of birth, dates of admission to the society's care, parents' names and addresses, status of parents, and comment on final disposition of the child. Also included in this collection are certificates of indentures and placement in the Orphan Asylum from the 19th century, proclamations from the State of New York and Borough of Brooklyn, and enlarged publicity photographs used for society publications and appear to have been hung in the organization's offices.
Adoption agencies -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Annual reports; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Certificates; Child welfare -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Children -- Institutional care; East Islip (N.Y.); Family social work -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Foster care -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Group homes for children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Orphanages -- New York (State) -- East Islip; Orphanages -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Orphans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Photographs; Registers (lists); Brookwood Child Care; Collins, Janna; Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn
- Series 1: Annual reports and manuals, 1834-1998
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1: Annual reports and manuals, 1834-1998, includes mostly Manuals and Annual Reports, along with a 1951 Biennial Report and Acts of Incorporation and By-laws from 1834 and 1933-1945. The Manuals run from 1860-1907 and the Annual Reports run from 1908 to 1998. These materials provide financial data, advisory board member names, and personnel information. While lists of contributors and society members are provided in annual reports, names of children in the society's care are not provided.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged chronologically.
  - Constitution and By-laws and Annual Report, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manual, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Manuals, 1861-1866 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Manuals, 1868-1872 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Manuals, 1873-1876 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Manuals, 1877-1880 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Manuals, 1881-1884 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Manuals, 1885-1888 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Manuals, 1889-1892 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Manuals, 1893-1896 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Manuals, 1897-1900 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Manuals, 1901-1904 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Manuals, 1905-1907 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports, 1908-1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1912-1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1916-1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1921-1924 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1925-1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports, 1932-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Acts of incorporation and by-laws, 1933-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Reports, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual Reports, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Annual Reports, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Annual Reports, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Biennial Report, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Annual Reports, 1949-1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports, 1956-1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports, 1974-1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1991-1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bound volume of manuals, 1834-1885 (Box 5, Volume 1)
  - Bound volume of manuals, 1885-1900 (Box 6, Volume 1)
- Series 2: Promotional materials, circa 1910-1986
  Series 2: Promotional materials, circa 1910-1986, includes printed materials used to promote the Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn and Brookwood Child Care. The bulk of this series are souvenir programs and booklets from anniversary dinners from 1926 to 1986.
  - Souvenir Photo Album, circa 1910 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Donation requests, 1918 - circa 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 93rd Anniversary, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 94th Anniversary, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 96th Anniversary, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 97th Anniversary, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 100th Anniversary history booklet, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Courier newsletter, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 125th Anniversary history booklet, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 150th Anniversary history booklet, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 152nd Anniversary, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 153rd Anniversary, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series 3: Citations and proclamations, 1983-1990
  Series 3: Citations and proclamations, 1983-1990, includes citations and proclamations from the Brooklyn Borough President and the State of New York Executive Chamber on the occasion of the Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn's 150th anniversary in 1983 (then Brookwood Child Care). There is also a proclamation from the State of New York Executive Chamber naming April 1990 the Month of the Child in recognition of the organization; and a proclamation from the Brooklyn Borough President naming May 23, 1985 Brookwood Child Care Day.
  This series is arranged in one folder.
  - Citations and proclamations, 1983-1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series 4: Register and certificates of indenture, 1855-1974
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to sensitive personal information, these materials are not open for research. Information from these materials can be requested on a case by case basis with a signed Center for Brooklyn History confidentiality agreement.
  Series 4: Register and certificates of indenture, 1855-1974, includes an Orphan Asylum and Brookwood Hall Register, dated 1907 to 1974, which lists orphan names, dates of birth, dates of admission to the society's care, parents' names and addresses, status of parents, and comment on final disposition of the child. Also included are certificates of indenture and a certificate confirming the placement of children in the care of the Orphan Asylum.
  - Certificates of indenture, 1855-1880 (Box 8 [RESTRICTED], Folder 1)
  - Copy of register, 1907-1974 (Box 8 [RESTRICTED], Folder 2)
  - Register, 1907-1974 (Box 8 [RESTRICTED], Volume 1)
- Series 5: Photographs, circa 1900-circa 1990
  Series 5: Photographs, circa 1900-circa 1990, includes photographs of children in the care of the Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn and Brookwood Child Care, the attending physician in 1881, and exterior and aerial photographs of the building at Atlantic Avenue and Brookwood Hall on Long Island.
  - Photographs, circa 1900 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1900 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, circa 1900 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, circa 1900 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, circa 1930 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, circa 1990 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Aerial view of building on Atlantic Avenue, Brooklyn, circa 1930 (Flat file folder 1 of 3)
  - View of Brookwood Hall, Long Island, circa 1942 (Flat file folder 2 of 3)
  - Aerial view of Brookwood Hall, Long Island, circa 1942 (Flat file folder 3 of 3)